<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: stuff | while true live]]></title>
  <link href="http://sleepomeno.github.io/blog/categories/stuff/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sleepomeno.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-07T15:23:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://sleepomeno.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gregor Riegler]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Blogging Matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://sleepomeno.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/Why-Blogging-Matters/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://sleepomeno.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/Why-Blogging-Matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is that fancy phrase &ldquo;pics or it didn&rsquo;t happen&rdquo;. It&rsquo;s just
claiming evidence for a, more or less, hardly credible experience which has often to do
with some sort of drug abuse. Yes, experience shows it&rsquo;s
sometimes cleverer to do without taking a photo, anyway, it crossed my mind that that phrase might be
applicable not only to excess-like experiences but to&hellip; pretty much
everything in life.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I&rsquo;ll come back later to what that actually means.. actually, I&rsquo;ve just found a nice <a href="http://mdswanson.com/blog/2013/08/11/write-things-tell-people.html" target="_blank">blog post</a>
about the importance of running a blog as a developer which goes
nicely with what I&rsquo;ve been thinking. The author, Matt Swanson, says
&ldquo;Do things, write about it&rdquo; and explains how sharing his learning on
his blog has been incredibly rewarding: Firstly, people told him how much they
enjoy reading his posts (those compliments alone may be worth it!) and secondly, he gained reputation by
demonstrating his abilities and initiative. As a result, he somehow became some
sort of a &ldquo;super hero&rdquo; in people&rsquo;s minds although his posts are not
exactly rocket-science. Regular posts (content is still king!) and a
pretty straight-forward way of expressing things were enough to raise
his value&hellip; the question is: Did Matt just fool his readers? Isn&rsquo;t he a clever guy after all?</p>

<p>Of course he is &ldquo;clever&rdquo;. He is &ldquo;clever&rdquo; <strong>because</strong> he shares his
projects, learnings and insights on his blog. Being a Software
developer, blogging about your projects is the most efficient way of
gaining an over-all reputation &ndash; a manager, who considers hiring you, won&rsquo;t read commit logs of Open Source
Projects where your name might appear but he can enjoy a well-written blog! In fact,
the &lsquo;positive&rsquo; effect on the manager&rsquo;s decision seems inevitable; and that&rsquo;s
where the &ldquo;pics or it didn&rsquo;t happen&rdquo; attitude comes into play. In
order to convey your abilities to the manager you need definite proof,
pretty similiar to the situation in court, actually: In the end, the
judge reaches a verdict and <strong>decides what is the truth</strong>. Analogously,
you will always <strong>be</strong> exactly as &ldquo;clever&rdquo; as your vis-à-vis, respectively the
readers of your blog, think you are! It goes without saying that you
can replace the word &ldquo;clever&rdquo; with whatever other positive quality you&rsquo;d
like to convey &ndash; &ldquo;competent&rdquo;, &ldquo;open-minded&rdquo;, &ldquo;innovative&rdquo;, &hellip;, you
name it.</p>

<p>Funnily enough, you will actually get cleverer when you blog regularly
;&ndash;) Strange? Well, first let&rsquo;s get rid of the word &ldquo;clever&rdquo; once and
for all, it is somehow inaccurate &ndash; what I want to say is: You will
get better at those topics you&rsquo;re blogging about. (And that not only
applies to tech blogs!) The reason for that: The extra thinking
necessary for presenting your work in a nicely structured way on your
blog will actually force you to nicely structure your projects as
well! In addition, your inner urge to at least blog once, twice or X
times a week will actually force you to pursue your projects and
learnings &lsquo;cause otherwise you wouldn&rsquo;t have anything to blog about.
As a result, you&rsquo;ll inevitably get better at reasoning and get a
better understanding of your blog posts&rsquo; topics&hellip; briefly, you get
&ldquo;cleverer&rdquo;! Isn&rsquo;t that ironic? ;&ndash;)</p>

<p>Anyway, I haven&rsquo;t been able to post regularly in the past, for
whatever reasons. In the end that always led to abandonning my past blogs altogether, so I&rsquo;m not
quite sure the above argumentation is too believable coming from me,
to be honest. However, for the moment, it is enough motivation for me to try a fresh
start with this blog. After all, it&rsquo;s all about motivation and inspiration.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A fresh start]]></title>
    <link href="http://sleepomeno.github.io/blog/2014/02/06/A-fresh-start/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://sleepomeno.github.io/blog/2014/02/06/A-fresh-start</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2014 has just started a month ago and I&rsquo;ve painfully realized that I
didn&rsquo;t come up with any New Year&rsquo;s resolutions at that time. There is
no resolution to violate, consequently, no reason to feel bad at all &ndash;
so why not start a new blog which I could then feel bad about when I
post nothing for months?! Well, to be serious, that&rsquo;s at least how all
my blogging attempts have ended so far. I definitely don&rsquo;t know if
history will repeat itself again this time. Maybe this post will actually stay the
only post for two months? Any bets? ;&ndash;)</p>

<p>Anyway, I better shortly summarize what I plan blogging about. Being a
software developer, tech topics will probably dominate. Still I can&rsquo;t
promise not to rant about some random topic from time to time ;&ndash;) As
an Emacs user I might blog about my <strong>Elisp</strong> learning progress or other
stuff like the one and only <strong>org-mode</strong>. Using <strong>Octopress</strong> as my blogging
engine it will be unavoidable to mention it as well, ranging from
plugins and customizations to its philosophy. From time to time I&rsquo;d also
like talking about my journeys to <strong>Haskell</strong> wonderland and
<strong>Clojure(Script)</strong> development. Or mention some Android apps? There are
enough topics for sure, we&rsquo;ll see if there is enough motivation to
carry on blogging as well ;&ndash;)</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s hope the best!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
