<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: setup | while true live]]></title>
  <link href="http://sleepomeno.github.io/blog/categories/setup/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sleepomeno.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-10T22:10:52+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://sleepomeno.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gregor Riegler]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using XMonad with a projector]]></title>
    <link href="http://sleepomeno.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/Using-XMonad-with-a-projector/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://sleepomeno.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/Using-XMonad-with-a-projector</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been using XMonad for a few years now (lately in combination with
GNOME) but just recently I have found a way to make it work in a useful way
in the context of a presentation with a projector as a second screen.</p>

<p>In general, XMonad does have decent multi-screen support. Building on
Xinerama, the default configuration provides key-binding support for
three screens; how workspaces are mapped to the screens and how this
mapping can change, respectively, can be pretty confusing at first, though &ndash;
it is best explained in <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/xmonad/comments/ndww5/dual_screens_multi_monitors_tips_and_tricks/c38dsfx" target="_blank">here</a>. Whenever I want to use a projector
things get pretty tricky, however.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The thing is: Using a projector as a second screen, I want to have
exactly the same workspace (accordingly the same windows, same layout,
obviously) on both screens. Apparently, I could do that by &lsquo;mirroring&rsquo;
the screens and thus circumventing XMonad multi-screen support. I&rsquo;m
not too happy with it, though, as, for some reason, I can&rsquo;t get <em>xrandr</em>
make show a reasonable resolution on both screens in that scenario &ndash;
part of what is shown on own screen is hidden on the other. Disabling
mirroring, however, it is <strong>impossible</strong> for XMonad to show exactly the
same on both screens &ndash; obviously, this is a restriction imposed by
Xinerama as it manages all workspaces across screens as <em>one</em>
large workspace under the hood.</p>

<p>The cure for that disease is the trick I found in another reddit
thread:
<a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/xmonad/comments/2ha25r/same_workspaces_on_multiple_monitors_without/ckrobfj" target="_blank">same workspaces on multiple monitors</a>.
So let&rsquo;s assume the following setup: Workspace 1 is shown on your
projector screen, Workspace 2 is shown on your internal screen. You
start a VNC server on workspace 1 on localhost:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>x11vnc -usepw -clip xinerama0 -noxdamage -geometry 1920x1080</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>(You might need to replace &lsquo;xinerama0&rsquo; by &lsquo;xinerama1&rsquo;. &lsquo;1920x1080&rsquo;
conforms to the resolution of my internal screen. &lsquo;-noxdamage&rsquo; is
optional but seems to be recommended.)</p>

<p>On Workspace 2 you start a VNC client:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>vncviewer ViewOnly=1 UseLocalCursor=0 localhost:0</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>(Again you might need to replace &lsquo;localhost:0&rsquo; by &lsquo;localhost:1&rsquo;.)</p>

<p>Well, now you get to see your projected presentation on your internal screen,
too, showing the X display of your VNC server screen! Move to Workspace 1 and start your presentation (or your live
coding, for example) while you actually watch your presentation on your internal screen on Workspace
2! As a bonus, during your presentation you could easily do things
which are not intended to be shown by the projector and/or move
windows from an internal workspace to Workspace 1 when they need to be shown.</p>

<p>Starting the vncviewer with the &lsquo;ViewOnly&rsquo; option makes it necessary
that you actually make your live in-presentation changes on Workspace
1, as I said (while watching your own changes on Workspace 2 on your
internal screen). That&rsquo;s my recommendation anyway, in my experience the viewer setup thus works more
stable and some keyboard inputs wouldn&rsquo;t be translated correctly from
the viewer to the server using a non-ViewOnly mode.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
